Reference counting. What is it? How does
it work? And why not just use SCD shared
pointer? That is what we're talking
about today. It's probably the number
one question that people have when they
see Hazel's codebase. What is this ref
thing? Now, I want to quickly clear up a
misconception. So, in Hazel, the game
engine series version of Hazel, this
which is a public GitHub repository, we
do have inside base.h ref being defined
as a shared pointer. So in this like
free 2D game engine series version of
Hazel, ref is in fact a shared pointer.
However, inside real Hazel, so this is
inside the big proper Hazel, ref is
actually a class, a class that we are
going to take a look at in more detail
over here. In this video, I thought that
it would make more sense to explain the
concept of reference counting by taking
a look at some examples. As we look at
the examples, I'll explain more of it.
We'll dive into the internals of how it
works and hopefully that will help some
of you who have never encountered this
sort of thing before. But fundamentally,
reference counting solves the problem of
I have an object that I eventually want
to be destroyed, but I'm not quite sure
when and how. And either way, I don't
want to handle that. It's supposed to be
a mechanism for automatic memory
management. But I want to stress that
sometimes this particular way of
automatically managing your memory is
your only option because sometimes you
don't really know exactly when or who
will be last to use a particular memory
allocation before it can be freed. So
diving into this, what do I have here? I
have a resource that I would like to be
heap allocated and then used for some
sort of lifetime. when everyone who is
using this resource is done with it, I
would like it to be deleted because no
one's using it anymore. The idea is that
this particular way of creating a
resource is sort of replacing just a
regular heap allocation. So if I did
something like this or that, I would of
course have to then at some point delete
it. This just automates that. Why?
because this ref class will inside the
create function actually create my new
object on the heap and then eventually
when the reference count hits zero it
will be deleted. So you can see that
this new and delete is just being
automatically done. It's abstracted away
into this ref class. Now there are many
different ways that we can sort of
automate or abstract new and delete. Of
course we could use a unique pointer. We
could even use a shared pointer in this
case. We'll talk about the nuances of
those specific other techniques. We'll
call them later in this video. But that
is the gist of how this works. This
isn't actually a compile error, by the
way. This is just Visual Studio. Okay.
So, to explain the actual concept of
reference counting, it works like this.
It's simply a way to track how many
different things are using your resource
with the idea being that once the
reference count hits zero, nothing is
using your resource and therefore it can
be freed. So to demonstrate this
practically in this case when we create
this resource exactly one thing is using
it this this variable resource is
holding our actual resource that is our
one reference to it. So therefore the
reference count is one. When we then
want to print it what are we doing here?
We're grabbing this resource variable
and we are passing it by value. We're
copying it into this print ref count
function. So therefore at this point
within this scope over here the
reference count of resource is two. Then
we print it. So we should see two in the
console. And then when we hit this and
we return back over here this particular
resource variable that was created by us
copying our original resource variable
into this function is now gone. It's
it's dead. It's been destroyed. And so
our reference count falls back down to
one. Then we hit the end of this scope
and this resource variable is now done.
It's destroyed. And so the reference
count of our actual resource that is
held within this resource variable goes
down to zero at which point it gets
destroyed. And so by the time we hit
this print line function over here, our
reference count is zero. But also the
actual object has been destroyed. Now
what is resource? resource is a very
very basic class that just simply says
that it was constructed destroyed and
for a more complicated example later in
this video we have this as well. You may
also notice that this is actually
deriving from a class called ref
counted. More on that later. So if I do
actually run this program then you will
see the result. So we construct the
resource which happens over here. We
print the resource ref count which it is
two as I explained. Then after this
function returns, the reference count
goes back down to one. We hit the end of
the scope. The reference count goes down
to zero. Our resource is destroyed. And
then finally, our program ends. If I
just pull this out and paste it into
here and here, then this becomes a
little bit more clearer. We construct
the resource. We have a reference count
of one. We put it into this function. It
goes up to two. It gets destroyed. Goes
back down to one. And that's it. So
ultimately, this ref object just simply
holds the pointer. So we have a pointer
of a particular type. This is our heap
allocation. This is what the ref class
holds. That's all it is. It's just
holding a pointer and it's providing all
of this functionality around that
pointer. What about the actual reference
count? Well, that is stored in the
actual resource. So in the resource
class itself, it derives from ref
counted. And the reason for that is
because this has the reference count.
It's just a normal unsigned integer. It
is atomic because multi-threading is a
thing. However, ultimately it's just a
uint 32t. You can see it starts at zero.
We have increment and decrement ref
count. And when the ref class is
actually constructed with a valid
nonnull pointer, then we will increment
the reference count, which simply calls
increment reference count on the actual
object. Now, how can we speak about
memory management without even
mentioning Rust, the language that fixes
[music] it all? Well, at least tries to
make it better. Why don't you find out
for yourself and just learn Rust with
Let's Get Rusty, the sponsor of this
video. Let's Get Rusty focuses
specifically on Rust education and job
ready training made by a fellow YouTuber
with a YouTube channel all about Rust.
If you're used to a low-level language
like C or C++, Rust builds on that and
tries to improve it with modern tooling,
which helps greatly with safety and
things [music] like threads.
Multi-threading can be difficult and the
strong safety guarantees built into Rust
can help improve [music] safety. All of
this is exactly why companies like
Google, Microsoft, and Amazon are
adopting Rust more and more in
production and developers really enjoy
using it. It keeps topping Stack
Overflow's most admired language year
after year. Let's get Rusty runs
structured programs for individuals and
teams. And over the years, they've
helped thousands of developers actually
learn Rust, become productive [music]
using Rust, not just watch endless
tutorials and forget everything a week
later. And here's the good news. They're
actually running a new cohort next
month. Spots are limited. Now is a
really great time to check [music] it
out. Go to let's
getrusty.com/startwithcher.
Link will be in the description below to
find out more about their training. Huge
thank you to let's get rusty for
sponsoring this video. Now, this ref
counted thing is kind of critical
because this is the biggest reason for
how this differs from what C++ already
provides you with. The biggest question
I get surrounding this is why do I not
just use a shared pointer? Because this
could just be a shared pointer and then
you would have std make shared and
that's it. Isn't that the same thing?
Well, kind of. It works the same way,
but it's different in a few crucial
ways. The biggest difference is that
shared pointer is not intrusive
reference counting. It stores the
reference count not as part of the
object but elsewhere. Make shared
combines the allocation of the actual
object and the reference counting block
into one allocation, but it's still not
intrusive. There's nothing in C++ that
exists at the moment that is actually
intrusive reference counting. The
closest thing that's kind of widely
available is something called boost
intrusive pointer, but we don't want to
use boost. Now, there is actually
something inside the standard library
called enable shared from this. This is
the closest thing to intrusive reference
counting, but the reference count is
still not actually in here. You can see
it's just holding a weak pointer. It's
just that it allows you to make a shared
pointer out of yourself. So I have an
example here that we'll look at in a
minute. But basically what I'm talking
about is this over here where we can
make a shared pointer of our particular
resource from this because otherwise
that's not really possible. So if you
had your shared pointer over here but
then I wanted to actually be inside the
resource class and then make a shared
pointer out of myself to then submit
somewhere. For example, I'll show you an
example from Hazel in a minute which
will make more sense. If I had something
like this where I wanted to submit
myself, you know, to the renderer and
then obviously the renderer will have to
use me. So I want it to be reference
counted because I don't know when the
renderer will finish with me. I can do
this by doing shared from this if I
subclass it. So this is the closest
thing to intrusive reference counting
like behavior that we have but still the
reference count is not really inside us.
So it's a bit different and basically
worse. Here's a more concrete example
from Hazel. So if we are in render
command buffer which is a ref countered
class and we want to submit ourselves to
the renderer because this needs to run
on the render thread then I can make a
reference counted object out of myself
and since the reference count is part of
this object it's not like oh I don't
know what my reference count is because
it's external. No, it's here. I am the
reference count. So therefore of course
you can make this ref object out of me.
I'll just increment the reference count
and then pass it off. hand it off onto a
different thread. And of course, we're
in a different thread now. So, we don't
know. Maybe the main thread will finish
with this first, but then the thread is
still holding on to it. So, in that
scenario, we literally don't know who's
going to finish with this because it's
all like multi-threaded race conditions,
whatever else. Let's look at an example
I prepared that is multi-threaded. So,
we have this multi-threaded example. Let
me shut off the other one and then we'll
take a look at this one. So, same story.
I have ref resource, but then what I'm
doing is creating four workers. These
are four worker threads. I'm going to
create one resource and I'm going to
give it to the worker threads. So each
thread is getting its own copy of this
ref, but it's still the same resource.
There's only one resource. I've created
it once. I'm just giving it to four
different workers that need to do things
with it. What the workers are actually
doing with it is simulating some work
that's happening. It's calling use on
the actual resource, which is just
simply printing which worker is
currently using it. we have this per
thread random number generator that will
simulate some sort of work for up to 100
milliseconds. So it'll just sleep and
then it will finish back on the main
thread. We will of course wait for all
of these workers to actually complete
before we try and end our program. And
then this is in a scope because as soon
as we unleash the workers, we're kind of
done with this resource. We don't really
need it on the main thread anymore.
We're happy to not use it on the main
thread, but the workers are still going
to need it. And specifically, we don't
really know which worker will finish
last with the resource, do we? Because,
well, in this case, we're simulating a
random amount of work. So, which worker
will finish last? Let's have a look at
how this program runs. So, we construct
the resource. Worker 1 2 3 and four and
zero actually had me going there. 1 2 3
and zero have all begun. They're all
using the resource. So, they've called
that use function. And then they're
sleeping for a random amount of time.
They're processing, let's just say, for
a random amount of time. Worker two
finishes first. Of course, it would
because it only took 5 milliseconds.
Then 3, 1, and zero. Then the resource
gets destroyed. So notice how zero,
worker zero finished last in this case.
Let's run it again. This time, worker
three finished last and then the
resource was destroyed. So you're kind
of seeing the picture here with the
lifetime pretty clearly, I hope. We
don't know the lifetime. We don't really
know when exactly and who exactly should
be responsible for this resource being
destroyed. All we know is that when
everyone is done with it, we want it to
be destroyed. When it's no longer
needed, we want it to be destroyed.
That's that's the definition of memory
management. When it's not needed,
destroy it. And that is what reference
counting does. That's what shared
pointers do because shared pointers are
an implementation of reference counting.
They're just not intrusive reference
counting. And again, if you want
intrusive reference counting, you have
to use your own or use boost. But wait,
let's not come on. Come on. Let's not
talk about that. And that is why Hazel
has this ref class. Now, if we look at a
shared pointer example of the same
thing, it would look exactly as you
would imagine. We would just be creating
shared pointers instead of refs. And
it's largely the same. But we can't do
things like this without enabling shared
from this. But then even so, it's still
not intrusive reference counting. I hope
you're getting the idea. If you guys
enjoyed this video, please don't forget
to hit the like button below. Let me
know what you want to see next as far as
C++ goes. This series is still alive and
I'm still going to try and make videos
when I have time. If you're interested
in reference counting and you want to
learn more about it, I highly recommend
you try and implement it yourselves.
This video should have given you enough
information to try and implement it
yourselves. I mean, the concept is
really simple. When you create a copy of
a ref, you increment the reference
count. When a ref dies, you decrement
the reference count. If it hits zero,
delete the underlying object. That's it.
Lots of nuances will creep up, but
that's the basic idea. So, give it a
shot. From here, there are other things
that exist within Hazel, such as weak
pointers, weak references, because you
may want to use this like a weak pointer
from a shared pointer. If you want to
see a video about how that works, let me
know in the comment section below. Thank
you guys for watching. I will see you
next time. Goodbye.